<?xml version='1.0'?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY copyright SYSTEM "copyright.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY BSD SYSTEM "BSD.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY GPL SYSTEM "GPL.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY LGPL SYSTEM "LGPL.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.8"> 
  <!ENTITY date "Aug 2004"> 
  <!ENTITY appversion "4.1.x"> 
]>

<article id="xfce4-user-guide" lang="en">

<!-- Header -->
<articleinfo>

<title>
  The Xfce 4 Desktop Environment
</title>

<subtitle>
  <inlinegraphic fileref="images/link_xfce.jpg"/>
  <emphasis>... and mice fly ...</emphasis>
</subtitle>

  <copyright>
    <year>2004</year> 
    <holder>Jasper Huijsmans</holder>
  </copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

  <copyright>
   <year>2002</year> <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin
   translation)</holder>
  </copyright>

 -->

<!-- I don't know about this
  <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
    <para>
      This document is provided under the terms of the GNU GPL, version
      2 or (at your option) any later version.
    </para>
  </legalnotice>
-->
  
<authorgroup>

<author>
  <firstname>Jasper</firstname>
  <surname>Huijsmans</surname>
 
  <affiliation>
    <address><email>huysmans@users.sourceforge.net</email></address>
  </affiliation>
</author>
  
</authorgroup>

<!--
<revhistory>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
    <date>May 2003</date>
    <authorinitials>jbh</authorinitials>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>0.1</revnumber>
    <date>2001-07-06</date>
    <authorinitials>jbh</authorinitials>
  </revision>
</revhistory>
-->

</articleinfo>

<!-- 

  Outline of the Xfce 4 User Guide
  ================================

  Preface
  ~~~~~~~
  This document gives an overview of the Xfce 4 Desktop Environment and
  explains how to perform several common tasks.

  Introduction
  ~~~~~~~~~~~~
  - General info
  - History
  - Resources

  Installation
  ~~~~~~~~~~~~
  - binary packages
  - sources
  - CVS

  Using Xfce 4
  ~~~~~~~~~~~~
  - Starting: startxfce4, customizing
  - Default desktop: components
  - How to: 
	* start programs (panel and root menu)
	* manage windows and workspaces (wm and taskbar)
	* use the settings manager
  
  Other Documents
  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
  - all module specific docs

  Copyright and Licence
  ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
  - copyright
  - BSD, GPL, LGPL

-->

<sect1 id="preface">
  
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para>
    This document gives an overview of the Xfce 4 Desktop Environment and
    explains how to perform several common tasks. It is meant to be a starting
    point for anyone who wants to use Xfce 4 and it includes pointers
    to other sources of information.
  </para>

  <para>
    The latest version of this document can always be found at this location:
<ulink url="http://www.loculus.nl/xfce/documentation/xfce4-user-guide.html" 
  type="html">http://www.loculus.nl/xfce/documentation/xfce4-user-guide.html</ulink>.
  </para>
  
</sect1>

<sect1 id="xfce4-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>Xfce is a lightweight desktop environment for unix-like operating
    systems. It aims to be fast and lightweight, while still being 
    visually appealing and easy to use.
  </para>

  <para>Xfce 4 is a complete rewrite of the previous version. It's based 
    on the GTK+ toolkit version 2. Xfce 4 has a radically different 
    architecture from Xfce 3. It embodies the traditional UNIX philosophy of 
    modularity and re-usability. All of Xfce 4's core components have been 
    written from scratch in order to fit into the new architecture.
  </para>

  <para>
    Another priority of Xfce 4 is adhereance to standards, specifically those
    defined at <ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org" 
      type="html">freedesktop.org</ulink>. This allows Xfce 4 to seamlessly
    interoperate with programs written for other desktop environments, if
    those programs follow the specified standards.
  </para>

  <para>Xfce 4 consists of a number of components that together provide the 
    full functionality of the desktop environment. They are packaged separately 
    and you can pick and choose from the available packages to create the best
    personal working environment.
  </para>

  <para>Xfce is all free software. The separate components are released under
    either the BSD license, the GNU LGPL or the GNU GPL (see <xref 
      linkend="xfce4-copyright"/> for details).
  </para>

  <sect2 id="xfce4-resources">
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>If you are looking for specific information about Xfce 4, chances are
      you can obtain it from one of these resources:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>The
	<ulink url="http://www.xfce.org" type="http">Xfce website</ulink>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>The Xfce 
	<ulink url="http://lunar-linux.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce" 
	  type="http">mailing list</ulink>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>The Xfce 4 development 
	<ulink url="http://lunar-linux.org/mailman/listinfo/xfce4-dev" 
	  type="http">mailing list</ulink>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>
  
</sect1>

<sect1 id="xfce4-install">
  <title>Installing Xfce4</title>

  <sect2>
    <title>Components of Xfce 4</title>
    
    <para>The Xfce 4 components are packaged separately. At the time of this
      writing the following modules are available.
    </para>

     
      <variablelist>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>libxfce4util</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Library with non-graphical helper functions.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	      
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>libxfcegui4</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Widget library and X Window System interaction.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	      
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>libxfce4mcs</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Settings management library used by most Xfce 4 modules.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>


	    
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce-mcs-manager</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Settings manager. Provides a control center for 
	      settings manager plugins that are installed by other modules.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	      
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce-mcs-plugins</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Settings manager plugins. These plugins provide settings 
	      dialogs for general items that are not part of a package, e.g. 
	      GTK settings, mouse settings, keyboard settings and display settings.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		  
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfwm4</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The Xfce 4 window mananger. Manages the placement of 
	      application windows on the screen, provides window decorations 
	      and manages workspaces or virtual desktops.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		  
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-panel</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The Xfce 4 panel. Provides program lauchers, a workspace
	      switcher, a clock, panel menus and more.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		  
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfdesktop</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Desktop background manager. This program sets the background 
	      image and/or color, and provides a root window menu along with its editor.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		  
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce-utils</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Essential utilities and scripts. Provides a taskbar, the
	      Xfce 4 about dialog, a run dialog and several important scripts 
	      that are used by other packages including the panel. Also 
	      contains this user guide.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xffm</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>A fast file manager, with double pane and integrated samba network browser.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfprint</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Print dialog. Provides a graphical frontend for printing.
	      Includes <application>xfprint4</application> and 
	      <application>xfprint-manager</application>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>gtk-xfce-engine-2</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Theme engine for GTK2. Not required for the desktop, but
	      it's a nice theme engine so you might just as well give it a try.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		
			<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-appfinder</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>An application finder, which allows you to search, launch and 
	    find informations about applications installed on your system. 
	    The applications are sorted by categories using .desktop files.
	    You can use xfce4-appfinder to drag and drop applications to 
	    the "Add launcher" menu item of the panel menus.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		
 	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfwm4-themes</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Window decoration themes for xfwm4.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xffm-icons</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Icon themes editor for the xffm file manager.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-themes</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Icon themes for the Xfce 4 panel.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-iconbox</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>An iconbox that can be used as an alternative for the
	      taskbar provided in the xfce-utils package. See <xref
		linkend="xfce4-getting-started"/> to find out how to modify 
	      the startup script.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
		  
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-mixer</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Volume control for the panel. Includes simple mixer dialog.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-systray</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Notification area or system tray for the panel. Note that
	      there can be only one system tray running at the time, so you
	      have to disable the system tray on the taskbar to use this panel
	      plugin.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-toys</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Less serious utilities and additions for the panel. 
	      Currently contains a tips/fortunes dialog and an xeyes 
	      implementation for the panel.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>xfce4-trigger-laucher</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Provides a toggle button for the panel, showing on or off
	      state. Check the README file provided in the package for more
	      information.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
    <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
</sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Binary packages</title>

    <para>The Xfce 4 project officially only releases source code for the
      desktop environment. However, binary packages may have been contributed
      by other people for your OS or distribution.
    </para>
    
    <para>Martin Loschwitz is the debian developer who maintains the Xfce 4
      packages for Debian unstable. Up-to-date versions should be available
      soon after the release.
    </para>

    <para>Look at the Xfce site for 
      <ulink url="http://xfce.org/index.php?page=download" 
	type="html">download locations</ulink> and additional information
      about available binary packages.
    </para>

    <para>If you could not find binary packages for your OS, they may be 
      available from your OS vendor or distributor, or you can install Xfce 4
      from source.
    </para>
   
  </sect2>

    <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
  <sect2>
    <title>Building from source</title>

    <para>Look at the Xfce site for 
      <ulink url="http://xfce.org/index.php?page=download" 
	type="html">download locations</ulink> for the source tarballs.
    </para>

    <para>Building the packages should be a simple matter of unpacking the
      tarballs and, from the top source directory, typing:
    
<programlisting>./configure &amp;&amp; make &amp;&amp; make install</programlisting>

      Some package will have extra configure options available. You can find 
      them by typing <command>./configure <option>--help</option></command>.
    </para>

    <para>Xfce 4 depends on pkg-config, GTK+ >= 2.2, libxml2 and, 
      for xffm, on libdbh, which is available from 
      <ulink url="http://sf.net/projects/libdbh" 
	type="html">SourceForge</ulink>. If you installed these from a binary
      package, make sure you have the corresponding <filename>-dev</filename>
      packages installed as well.
    </para>

    <para>Optionally you can install librsvg >= 2.2, for SVG icon support, and
      libstartup-notification, to have a busy cursor when loading applications
      that support this standard.
    </para> 

    <para>If you install into a different prefix from pkg-config, you have to
      set the PKG_CONFIG_PATH variable to include the path to the *.pc files
      installed by the Xfce 4 libraries, which is ${prefix}/lib/pkgconfig. For
      example:
    </para>

<programlisting>export PKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig</programlisting>

    <para>All source tarballs also contain a so called spec file that allows
      you to build your own rpm's:
<programlisting>rpmbuild -ta <filename>module-x.y.z.tar.gz</filename></programlisting>
    </para>

  </sect2>

    <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
  <sect2>
    <title>Using CVS</title>

    <para>The latest development sources for Xfce 4 are available from CVS.
    </para>
    
    <para>Look <ulink url="http://xfce.org/index.php?page=documentation&amp;lang=en#install"
	type="html">here</ulink> for information on how to obtain the latest
      development updates from CVS. You can also use the WebCVS link to browse 
      the CVS tree.
    </para>

  </sect2>
  
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
  <sect2>
    <title>Additional software</title>

    The <ulink url="http://xfce-goodies.berlios.de" 
      type="html">Xfce Goodies</ulink> project collects third-party
    contributions for Xfce 4. There are some excellent panel plugins available
    that greatly enhance the functionality of Xfce 4.
  </sect2>
   
  <para>&nbsp;</para>
    
</sect1>

<sect1 id="xfce4-use">
  <title>Using Xfce4</title>

  <sect2 id="xfce4-getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>Use <application>startxfce4</application> to start an Xfce session,
      which includes the session manager, the panel, the taskbar, the window 
      manager and the desktop manager. 
      All programs, or symbolic links to programs, in 
      <filename>~/Desktop/Autostart/</filename> will be run on startup.
    </para>

    <para>
      To customize the behaviour of <application>startxfce4</application>, 
      copy the file <filename>${sysconfdir}/xfce4/xinitrc</filename> to your 
      personal <filename>~/.xfce4/</filename> directory and edit that file.
    </para>

    <para>
      Depending on your installation method the location of the system
      <filename>xinitrc</filename> file may be different. If you 
      install from source, <filename>${sysconfdir}</filename> defaults to 
      <filename>/usr/local/etc</filename>. For binary packages it is often 
      set to <filename>/etc</filename>; you can use your package manager to
      find out.
    </para>

    <para>      
      Finally, the copied <filename>xinitrc</filename> file has to be made 
      executable:
      <programlisting>chmod u+x ~/.xfce4/xinitrc</programlisting>
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <para>&nbsp;</para>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>The Default Desktop</title>

    <para>The Xfce 4 Desktop Environment is not a single entity that provides
      all funtionality, but rather it tries to adhere to the old UNIX
      tradition of small tools that do one job and do it well. A default 
      Xfce 4 desktop with no programs running is shown in 
      <xref linkend="default-session-fig"/>.
    </para>
    
    <figure id="default-session-fig">
      <title>Default Xfce 4 session</title> 
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/default-session.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  <!-- 
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/default-session.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject> 
	  --> 
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Shows default Xfce session, with background manager, panel 
	      and taskbar.
	    </phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>When you run <application>startxfce4</application> several
      applications are started:
    </para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Taskbar</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>At the top of the screen you will see the taskbar. It shows
	    the applications running on the current workspace. You can
	    focus the application by clicking on the button in the taskbar.
	    Clicking the button again will hide the application. Moreover, if click on the button 
	    with the right button of the mouse, an menu will appear, allowing you to perform 
	    several actions on the	    	    	     application window. The taskbar
	    also contains a graphical pager showing a miniature view of all 
	    your workspaces. You can even move windows to another workspace by
	    draggin the miniwindow in the pager. Initially invisible is the
	    notification area or system tray. This will only do something when
	    an application uses a status icon. An example is the instant
	    messaging application <application>gaim</application>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Panel</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>At the bottom of the screen is the Xfce4 panel. It allows you
	    to run applications and also contains a graphical pager, a clock
	    and a mail checker. Some items have an associated panel menu that
	    gives access to more applications. Panel menus are opened by
	    pressing the small arrow buttons next to the associated panel item.
	    Changing the content of the panel and the properties of the items
	    is done by using the right mouse button. Both the panel items and
	    the panel move handles have a right-click mouse menu from where
	    you can chage the panel configuration. For more information look
	    at the <ulink url="xfce4-panel.html" type="html">panel
	      manual</ulink>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Desktop Manager</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The desktop manager provides the desktop background image and
	    two menus when you click on the desktop background.
	  </para>
	  <para>The right mouse button opens a menu that allows you to start 
	    applications. Look at the <ulink url="xfdesktop.html" 
	      type="html">manual</ulink> to find out how to change the menu 
	    contents.
	  </para>
	  <para>The middle mouse button (or Shift + left click) opens a list of
	    all applications that are currently running. You can activate an
	    application by clicking on its menu entry.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Window Manager</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The window manager is responsible for placing the windows on
	    the screen and provides the window borders and decorations. It
	    allows you to move windows around by draggin the titlebar and
	    provides title bar buttons, for example to close, minimize or
	    maximize a window. Look at the <ulink url="xfwm4.html"
	      type="html">manual</ulink> for a full explanation of the window 
	    manager.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
	<term>Settings Manager</term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The settings manager runs in the background and makes sure
	    that all Xfce 4 applications update their settings when the user 
	    changes something in the settings manager dialog (see following
	    section) and takes care of reading the configuration from disk at 
	    startup.	    
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Common Tasks</title>

    <para>This section will explain how to perform several common tasks to 
      quickly get you started working with Xfce 4. Because that is what
      Xfce 4 is designed for, to allow you to get work done.
    </para>

    <sect3>
      <title>Running programs</title>

      <variablelist>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Xfce 4 panel</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The panel is designed to allow quick access to the most
	      frequently used applications by putting them on the main panel.
	      Less often used applications can be put in a panel menu. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Desktop menu</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Another method for starting applications is from the desktop
	      mouse menu. Read the <application>xfdesktop</application> <ulink
		url="xfdesktop.html" type="html">manual</ulink> for
	      information on how to change the menu contents.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Run dialog</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>If you know the name of a program and it is not on the panel
	      or in the desktop menu you can use the run dialog. To open the
	      dialog type Alt-F2 or choose the 'Run
	      program...' option from the desktop menu.
	    </para>
	    <para>The dialog will remeber the 10 last commands that were
	      successfully executed.
	    </para>	      
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
      
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Managing windows and workspaces</title>

      <variablelist>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Basic window operations</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>You can move windows around the screen by dragging their
	      title bar. A window can be closed, hidden, maximized, shaded and
	      made sticky &mdash; this means it will show up on all workspaces
	      &mdash; by using the title bar buttons.
	    </para>
	    <para>Right clicking on the title bar will open a menu that gives
	      access to all window operations.</para>
	    <para>Shading a window, which means collapsing it to only show the
	      title bar, can also be accomplished by using the mouse wheel
	      over the title bar. Up is shade, down is unshade.
	    </para>
	    <para>If you want maximized windows to not cover the entire screen
	      you can set workspace margins from the settings manager dialog
	      (see below).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Application management</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To find out what applications are currently running you can
	      look at the taskbar. Clicking on a button in the taskbar will
	      focus the associated application. Clicking again will hide it.
	    </para>
	    <para>When you click with the middle mouse button on the desktop 
	      background a list of windows is shown, ordered by workspace. 
	      You can activate the application or change workspaces by 
	      choosing the appropriate menu entry.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      The <application>xfce4-iconbox</application> application can 
	      also be used to keep track of running applications.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Workspaces</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>You can change workspaces by clicking on them in the
	      graphical pager, either on the taskbar or on the panel. Pressing 
	      Ctrl-Alt-LeftArrow or Ctrl-Alt-RightArrow will cycle through the
	      workspaces. Using the mousewheel over the pager or the desktop
	      background will have the same effect.
	    </para>
	    <para>To add or remove workspaces you can use the middle click
	      desktop menu or the settings dialog (see below).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Using the settings manager dialog</title>

      <para>The settings manager dialog provides access to the global
	preferences of many Xfce 4 applications. You can run it by pressing 
	its laucher on the panel, from the right click menu on the panel
	move handles or from the desktop mouse menu.
      </para>

      <para>Preference dialogs for many aspects of the Xfce 4 desktop 
	environment are available. The available options are described in the 
	manuals of each Xfce 4 component. It may be interesting to have a quick
	look at all the dialogs to see all options that allow you to create 
	the best possible working environment.
      </para>

    </sect3>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Further reading</title>

    <para>This user guide has only given a very general overview of the Xfce 4
      Desktop Environment. More information is  available in the 
      <ulink url="index.html" type="html">manuals</ulink> of the separate
      components of Xfce 4.
    </para>

  </sect2>
  
</sect1>

&copyright;

&BSD;

&GPL;

&LGPL;

</article>


